THE WAY She looked at the key quite a long time. She turned it over and over, and
thought about it. As I have said before, she was not a child who had been trained
to ask permission or consult her elders about things. All she thought about the key was
that if it was the key to the closed garden, and she could find out where the
door was, she could perhaps open it and see what was inside the walls, and what
Haden happened to the old rose trees It was because it had been shut up
so long that she wanted to see it. It seemed as if it must be different from
other places and that something strange must have happened to it during 10
years. Besides that, if she liked it she could go into it every day and shut the
door behind her, and she could make up some play of her own and play it quite
alone, because nobody would ever know where she was, but would think the door
was still locked and the key buried in the earth. The thought of that pleased
her very much. Living as it were, all by herself in a house with a hundred
mysteriously closed rooms and having nothing whatever to do to amuse herself,
had set her inactive brain to working and was actually awakening her
imagination. There is no doubt that the fresh, strong, pure air from the Moore had
a great deal to do with it. Just as it had given her an appetite,
and fighting with the wind had stirred her blood, so the same things had stirred her
mind. In India she had always been too hot and languid and weak to care much
about anything, but in this place she was beginning to care and to want to do new
things. Already she felt less "contrary," though she did not know why.
She put the key in her pocket and walked up and down her
walk. No one but herself ever seemed to come there, so she could walk slowly and
look at the wall, or, rather, at the ivy growing on it. The ivy was the baffling
thing. Howsoever carefully she looked she could see nothing but thickly growing
glossy, dark green leaves. She was very much disappointed. Something of her
contrariness came back to her as she paced the walk and looked over it at the
Treetops inside. It seemed so silly, she said to herself, to be near it and not be
able to get in. She took the key in her pocket when she went back to the house,
and she made up her mind that she would always carry it with her when she went
out, so that if she ever should find the hidden door she would be ready. Mrs.
Medlock had allowed Martha to sleep all night at the cottage, but she was back at
her work in the morning with cheeks redder than ever and in the best of
spirits. "I got up at 4:00 she said. "Eh! it
was pretty on the mall with the birds getting up and the rabbit scampering
about and the sun rising I didn't walk
all the way. A man gave me a ride in his
cart and I can tell you I did enjoy myself." She was full of stories of the
delights of her day out. Her mother had been glad to see her and they had got
the baking and washing all out of the way. She had even made each of the
children a dough cake with a bit of brown sugar in it. "I had them all piping
hot when they came in from playing on the mall and the cottage all smelled a
nice, clean hot bacon and there was a good fire and they just shouted for joy.
Our Dickon he said our cottage was good enough for a king to live in."
In the evening they had all sat around the fire, and Martha and her mother had
sewed patches on torn clothes and mended stockings and Martha had told them about
the little girl who had come from India and who had been waited on all her life
by what Martha called "blacks" until she didn't know how to put on her own
stockings he they did like to hear about you," said Martha. "They wanted to know all
about the blacks and about the ship you came in.
I couldn't tell them enough." Mary reflected a little. "I'll tell you a great deal more
before your next day out," she said, "so that you will have more to talk about. I
dare say they would like to hear about riding on elephants and camels, and about
the officers going to hunt tigers." "My word!" cried delighted Martha. "It
would set them clean off their heads.
Would that really do do that, Miss? It would be same as a wild beast show like
we heard they had in York once." "India is quite different from
Yorkshire," Mary said slowly, as she thought the matter over. "I never thought
of that. Did Dickon and your mother like to hear you talk about
me?" "Why, our dickens's eyes nearly started out of his head, they got that round," answered
Martha. "But mother, she was put out about you're seeming to be all by yourself
like. She said, 'Hasn't Mr. Craven got no governor for her, nor no nurse?' and I said,
'No, he hasn't, though Mrs. Medlock says he will when he thinks of it, but she says
he may think of it for two or three years.'" "I don't want a govern us said Mary
sharply. "But mother says you ought to be learning your book by this time and you
ought to have a woman to look after you and she says: 'Now, Martha, you just think
how you'd feel yourself, in a place like that wandering about all alone and no
mother. You do your best to cheer her up,' she says and I said I
would." Mary gave her a long, steady look.
"You do cheer me up," she said. "I like to hear you
talk." Presently Martha went out of the room and came back with something held
in her hands under her apron. "What does thou think," she said, with
a cheerful grin. "I've brought thee a present." "A present!" exclaimed Mistress
Mary. How could a cottage full of 14 hungry people give anyone a
present! "A man was driving across the moall pedaling Martha explained and he
stopped his cart at our door. He had pots and pans and odds and ends, but mother
had no money to buy anything Just as he was going away our
Elizabeth Ellen called out, 'Mother, he's got skipping ropes with red and blue
handles a mother she calls out quite sudden, 'Here, stop, mister! How much are
they and he says tant and mother she began fumbling in her pocket and she
says to me, 'Martha that's brought me thy wages like a good lass and I've got four
places to put every penny, but I'm just going to take tant out of it to buy that
child a skipping rope and she bought one and here it is." She brought it out from
under her apron and exhibited it quite proudly. It was a strong, slender rope
with a striped red and blue handle at each end, but Mary Lennox had never seen a
skipping rope before. She gazed at it with a mystified expression. "What is it for?" she asked
curiously four cried out Martha. "Does that mean that they've not got skipping
ropes in India, for all they've got elephants and tigers and camels! No
wonder most of them's black. This is what it's for; just watch
me." And she ran into the middle of the room and, taking a handle in each hand,
began to skip, and skip, and skip, while Mary turned in her chair to stare at her,
and the queer faces in the old portraits seemed to stare at her, too, and wonder
what on earth this common little cottager had the impudence to be doing under their very
noses. But Martha did not even see them.
The interest and curiosity in Mistress Mary's face delighted her, and she went
on skipping and counted as she skipped until she had reached a 100 I could skip
longer than that," she said when she stopped. "I've skipped as much as 500 when
I was 12 but I wasn't as fat then as I am now and I was in
practice." Mary got up from her chair beginning to feel excited herself. "It
looks nice," she said said. "Your mother is a kind woman. Do you think I could ever
skip like that?" "You just try it," urged Martha, handing her the skipping
rope You can't skip a 100 at first, but if you practice you'll mount up. That's
what mother said. She says nothing will do her more good than skipping rope. It's
the Sensi blest toy a child can have. Let her play out in the fresh air skipping
and it'll stretch her legs and arms and give her some strength in
them It was plain that there was not a great deal of strength in Mistress
Mary's arms and legs when she first began to skip. She was not very clever at
it, but she liked it so much that she did
not want to stop. "Put on the things and run and skip out of doors," said Martha.
"Mother said I must tell you to keep out of doors as much as you could, even when
it rains a bit, so as that wrap up warm."
Mary put on her coat and hat and took her skipping rope over her arm. She
opened the door to go out, and then suddenly thought of something and turned back rather
slowly. "Martha," she said, "they were your wages. It was your tant really. Thank you."
She said it stiffly because she was not used to thanking people or noticing that
they did things for her. "Thank you," she said, and held out her
hand because she did not know what else to do. Martha gave her hand a clumsy
little shake, as if she was not accustomed to this sort of thing either.
Then she laughed a th art a queer old womanish thing," she said. "If that had been
our Elizabeth Ellen that would have given me a kiss." Mary looked stiffer than
ever. "Do you want me to kiss you?" Martha laughed again. "Nay, not me," she answered. "If
thou was different perhaps THD want to thy C But thou isn't. Run off outside and
play with thy rope." Mistress Mary felt a little awkward as she went out of the room. Yorkshire
people seemed strange, and Martha was always rather a puzzle to her. At first
she had disliked her very much, but now she did not. The skipping rope was a wonderful thing.
She counted and skipped, and skipped and counted, until her cheeks were quite red,
and she was more interested than she had ever been since she was
born. The sun was shining and a little wind was blowing— —not a rough wind, but
one which came in delightful little gusts and brought a fresh scent of newly turned earth with
it. She skipped around the fountain garden, and up one walk and down another.
She skipped at last into the kitchen garden and saw Ben Weatherstaff digging
and talking to his robin, which was hopping about him. She skipped down the
walk toward him and he lifted his head and looked at her with a curious
expression. She had wondered if he would notice her. She really wanted him to see
her skip. "Well!" he exclaimed. "Upon my word perhaps there are a young after all and
perhaps th got child's blood in thy veins instead of sour buttermilk th
skipped red into thy cheeks as sure as my name's Ben weather staff I wouldn't
have believed that could do it." "I never skipped before," Mary said. "I'm
just beginning. I can only go up to 20 thou keep on," said Ben thou shapes
well enough at it for a young that's lived with heathen. Just see how he's
watching thee," jerking his head towards the robin. "He followed after thee
yesterday. He'll be at it again today He'll be bound to find out what
the skipping rope is. He's never seen one.
Eh!" shaking his head at the bird thy curiosity will be the death of thee
sometime if th doesn't look sharp." Mary skipped round all the gardens and round
the orchard, resting every few minutes. At length she went to her own special walk
and made up her mind to try if she could
skip the whole length of it. It was a good long skip and she began slowly, but
before she had gone halfway down the path she was so hot and breathless that
she was obliged to stop. She did not mind much, because she had already counted up to
30 She stopped with a little laugh of pleasure, and there, lo and behold, was the
robin SW Weighing on a long branch of ivy. He had followed her and he greeted
her with a chirp. As Mary had skipped toward him she felt something heavy in her pocket
strike against her at each jump, and when she saw the robin she laughed again. "You
showed me where the key was yesterday," she said. "You ought to show me the door
today but I don't believe you know!" The robin flew from his swinging
spray of iy onto the top of the wall and he opened his beak and sang a loud,
lovely trill, merely to show off. Nothing in the world is quite as adorably lovely
as a robin when he shows off— —and they are nearly always doing it. Mary Lennox
had heard a great deal about Magic in her Aya's stories, and she always said
that what happened almost at that moment was Magic. One of the night ni little gusts
of wind rushed down the walk, and it was a stronger one than the rest. It was
strong enough to wave the branches of the trees, and it was more than strong
enough to sway the trailing sprays of untrimmed ivy hanging from the
wall. Mary had stepped close to the robin, and suddenly the gust of wind swung
aside some loose ivy trails, and more suddenly still she jumped toward it and
caught it in her hand.
This she did because she had seen something under it— —a round knob which
had been covered by the leaves hanging over it. It was the knob of a
door. She put her hands under the leaves and began to pull and push them
aside. Thick as the ivy hung, it nearly all was a loose and swinging curtain,
though some had crept over wood and iron. Mary's heart began to thump and her
hands to shake a little in her delight and excitement. The robin kept singing and
twittering away and tilting his head on one side, as if he were as excited as she
was. What was this under her hands which was square and made of iron and which
her fingers found a hole in? It was the lock of the door which had been closed
10 years and she put her hand in her pocket, drew out the key and found it
fitted the keyhole. She put the key in and turned it.
It took two hands to do it, but it did
turn. And then she took a long breath and looked behind her up the long walk to
see if anyone was coming. No one was coming. No one ever did come, it seemed,
and she took another long breath, because she could not help it, and she held back
the swinging curtain of ivy and pushed back the door which opened slowly— —slowly.
Then she slipped through it, and shut it behind behind her, and stood with her
back against it, looking about her and breathing quite fast with excitement, and wonder, and
delight. She was standing inside the secret
garden. CHAPTER